A Guide to the Martha K. Roane Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-ac
Martha K. Roane Papers ca. 1901-1989
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-ac
740 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection bears no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Martha K. Roane's husband, Curtis Roane, Blacksburg, Virginia, on May 27, 1997.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of Dr. Martha K. Roane(1921-1996), retired Adjunct Professor, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Department of Plant Pathology, Physiology, and Weed Science, and member of the American Rhododendron Society, Middle Atlantic Chapter, ca. 1901-1989, containing 740 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear shelf feet), pertaining to her study of rhododendrons, and containing manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence, negatives and photographs of microscopic views of rhododendrons, news clippings, and electrostatic copies of printed journal articles. The earliest dated materials are copies of articles and monographs about rhododendron research by leading experts in the field.
There are also individual files on publication by Martha K. Roane concerning rhododendrons which include: "Chromosome Numbers for Ericaceae in Virginia, "
Compendium of Rhododendron & Azalea Diseases
, "The Ericales of Virginia, " "The Lycopodiums -Running Pine, Ground Cedar and Other Club Mosses" in
The Virginia Explorer
, "Native American Rhododendrons: A Botanical Treasure," "A Revision of Kalmia, Menziesia, and Rhododendron in Virginia" and "The Species of Rhododendron Native to North America. " Other notable files include one with general correspondence about rhododendrons; the American Rhododendron Society Meeting in 1988; Diseases of Rhododendron and Azalea Slide Set Syllabus file; a miscellaneous papers file containing a vita for Roane, a copy of the notice of her death in the
Mid-Atlantic Rhododendron News and Notes
, news clippings, organizational bulletins, and a press release regarding the publication of a monograph on Chestnut Blight by Roane and two other researchers; and two folders of correspondence between Martha K. Roane and Miss Josephine de N. Henry of the Henry Foundation for Botanical Research, who co-authored "The Species of Rhododendron Native to North America" with Roane.
Martha Ann Kotila Roane(1921-1996) was born in Munising, Michigan, to John Ernest Kotila(1893-1951), who was also a plant pathologist, and Matha Olsen Kotila(d.1941). She attended Michigan State University(1940-1944, B.S.), the University of Minnesota(1945-1946, M.S.), the University of Michigan(1946-1947, graduate studies), and the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University(1968-1971, Ph.D.). Roane taught mathematics at both Radford College and the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University from 1956-1968, and biology, botany, and plant pathology at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University from 1970 until her retirement.
She was a member of the American Phytopathological Society, the Mycological Society of America, the American Rhododendron Society, the Virginia Academy of Science, Botany Section, and lists her major areas of interests as the taxonomy of higher plants (Ericaceae, especially rhododendron) and fungi (plant pathogenic fungi, especially endothia).
Item Listing
- American Rhododendron Society Meeting - 1988, 1986-1988 (Box Box 1)
- Articles re Rhododendrons, including one on mushrooms, 1930-1985 (Box Box 1)
- Articles re Rhododendrons, A-H, formerly collected in a three-ring binder, 1920-1973 (Box Box 1)
- Articles re Rhododendrons, J-L, formerly collected in a three-ring binder, 1954-1980 (Box Box 1)
- Articles re the Rhododendron Leaf, formerly collected in a three-ring binder, 1901-1970 (Box Box 1)
- Articles re Rhododendron Taxon, formerly collected in a three-ring binder, 1914-1971 (Box Box 1)
- "Chromosome Numbers for Ericaceae in Virginia" by Martha K. Roane, ca. 1985 (Box Box 1)
- Compendium of Rhododendron & Azalea Diseases, including manuscripts and correspondence, 1960-1987, n.d.; (8 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Compendium of Rhododendron & Azalea Diseases - Contract with the American Phytopathological Society, 1984-1985 (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1972-1989 (Box Box 3)
- Diseases of Rhododendron and Azalea Slide Set Syllabus compiled by Molly N. Cline and Martha Roane, 1987-1988 (Box Box 3)
- "The Ericales of Virginia" by Martha K. Roane, 1989 (Box Box 3)
- Excerpts from "Dwarf Rhododendrons" and "The Larger Species of Rhododendrons" by Peter A. Cox, 1973, 1979 (Box Box 3)
- "The Genera of Ericaceae in the Southeastern United States" by Carroll E. Wood, 1961 (Box Box 3)
- Henry Foundation for Botanical Research - Correspondence, 1971-1984, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
- "The Leaf Anatomy of Southeastern Shrub-bog Plants" by Joseph P. McMenamin, 1940 (Box Box 4)
- "The Lycopodiums - Running Pine, Ground Cedar and Other Club Mosses" in The Virginia Explorer by Martha Roane, 1987 (Box Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1970-1987 (Box Box 4)
- A Monograph of Azaleas Rhododendron Subgenus Anthodendron by Ernest Henry Wilson and Alfred Rehder, 1921 (Box Box 4)
- "Native American Rhododendrons: A Botanical Treasure" by Martha K. Roane, 1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
- Photographs of Rhododendrons under the microscope, 1973 (Box Box 4)
- "A Revision of Kalmia, Menziesia, and Rhododendron in Virginia" by Martha K. Roane, 1970 May 30 (Box Box 4)
- "The Species of Rhododendron Native to North America" by Martha Roane and Josephine de N. Henry", 1981 (Box Box 4)